So now your main task is just
那你现在主要就是
picking up the kids and buying groceries.
接孩子 买菜
No.
没有啊
I'm still out on marketing
我跑业务嘛
occasionally.
我偶尔也跑业务
I'm still at
我还是在
the research institute.
研究所里
You're facing challenges, aren't you?
你现在是不遇到瓶颈了
Right?
是不
Or bottleneck as they say it?
现在不都说瓶颈吗
It's like you can't move forward.
就是过不去了
You got stuck like here.
就是瓶在这儿
Right? Isn't that what it means?
是不 是不那意思
The road...
这科
The route to science is endless.
科学的道路永无止境嘛
Having a bottleneck is a good thing.
有瓶颈也是好事
Overcoming challenges
攻克难关
leads to new goals.
才有这个新的目标嘛
Can you talk to me about this?
那你能跟爸说说吗
About what?
说啥
The bottleneck.
瓶颈啊
Not at all.
没瓶颈啊
Our business
我们现在业务
is flourishing now.
都饱和着呢
Everything's good.
都 都挺好
A thing
一 一个东西
is researched,
它研究出来
isn't it?
它不 不是
It doesn't happen right away.
一时半会儿的事儿
It takes a long time.
它得很长时间
Even up to two or,
甚至这两年
five years,
五年
or possibly over ten years.
甚至十年以上都有可能
That means,
那就是说
it could take ten years to discover something.
研究个东西得十年
Wouldn't you starve to death by then?
那你不都饿死了
What kind of team
那你们这啥团队呀
is this?
你们这是
Hey,
不是
why are you always absent-minded?
你怎么老发呆呢
Even so in a chess.
你看你下个棋也发呆
I'm not zoning out.
我没发呆啊
I'm just contemplating.
我 我这琢磨它呢
Last time
上一次
when you helped me clean the pool,
你帮我刷这个池子
I saw you
我一看你手里头
holding the tap,
抱个水管子
not even turning it on.
你都没开开
You were absent-minded, weren't you?
那你说你不是发呆呢吗
I...
我
That's called clearing the mind,
那叫放空
a form of meditation.
一种修行
Again?
又发呆
I wasn't.
我没
I wasn't thinking.
没发呆
Actually, if there's anything,
其实有啥事吧
just say it.
就说一说呗
Remember, I'm your father-in-law.
你说我是你老丈人
You're not an outsider.
又不是外人
We're all family here.
就这一家人啊
If there's anything,
有啥事吧
don't keep it on your mind .
别在心里头闷着
If you can talk about it, then speak up.
能说就说出来
We'll help in the best way we can.
我们能帮点啥就帮点啥
Everyone has pressure
现在的生活呀
to live these days.
谁都有压力
Everyone is busy.
都是忙忙叨叨的
It's not easy for anyone.
都不容易啊
It's your turn.
到你了
Dad,
爸
don't worry.
您放心
I'm fine.
我没事
If there's anything,
要有什么事啊
I won't keep it inside.
我不憋着
I'll tell you.
我跟您说
Yes.
对
Even though I'm not your dad,
虽然我不是你爸
I'm still your father-in-law.
但是我是你老丈人
Right?
是不是
Let me tell you, Li Lin,
我跟你说 李临啊
I don't have a son,
我没儿子
but ever since
但是呢
you
自从你
married An,
跟安安结婚以后
do you know how I see you?
你知道我对你怎么看吗
As a saying goes in the Northeast,
我们东北的老话说呀
a son-in-law is like half a son.
一个姑爷半拉儿
But I
但是我
see you as a son.
是把你当一个儿子看
I treat you like my own son.
把你当儿子看
You're also a father to me.
您也是我爸
Abortion surgery harms your health.
流产手术很伤身体
Even if it's a miscarriage,
就是小产
You need to rest for at least
怎么也要休息个
one or two weeks.
一到两周
At your age, you still need to be careful.
你这个年纪还是要注意
Get some good rest and don't fall ill.
好好休息 别落下病
Mr. Zhang.
张总
How did it go?
怎么样了
It went smoothly.
挺顺利的
Mr. Xiao is quite pleased
肖总对新的营销方案
with the new marketing plan.
也很满意
Anyway, I provided
反正我把能用的资源
all the available resources for him.
全都给他堆上了
Keep the client for now.
先保住客户呗
How could you tell
你说你们怎么能
them the least price?
把底价给人透露出去啊
How much are we losing?
赔多少
Mr. Zhou is still calculating over there.
小周总那边还在核算
Alright,
行了
just tell me the remedial plan.
你就说补救方案吧
I'll handle this project myself.
这个项目我自己盯
Then,
然后
I'll go after two more clients.
我再去跑两个客户吧
You let me wait...?
我还等
Alright.
行了
Finish these two cases
你先把这两个案子
first.
做了吧
Let me tell you,
我跟你说了
we'll have wriggle room if you make it.
谈成了还有缓
If not,
谈不成
forget about next month's
下个月的工资奖金
salary and bonuses.
就别想了啊
We'll all go down together.
大伙抱着一起死吧
Your house,
你那个房子
when will it be completed?
什么时候交啊
My house
我那房子
won't be ready for another six months.
得半年以后才交付呢
Well, six months
不是 半年以后
will pass in the blink of an eye.
一晃就过去了
Right now,
你现在呀
you should make some time
抽时间
to visit the building materials market.
就得到那个建材城啊
Take a look around.
去逛一逛
You need to plan carefully.
你得想好了
Once you've decided,
想好了之后
you should quickly check out
你赶紧去那个
the decoration materials.
看那个装修材料啊
Sure, sure, sure.
我知道 知道 知道
Think about it,
你想一想
in one's lifetime,
人这一辈子
how many houses can one buy?
能买几套房子
Once you buy it, you'll live there forever,
你买了就得住一辈子
right?
是不是
Not just your lifetime,
你不光一辈子
your kids in the future,
你将来 你孩子以后
they'll live there too.
你也得住啊
Hey, I'm talking to you!
不 我跟你说话呢
Also, during the decoration,
另外装修的时候吧
you and An should
你跟这个安安俩吧
discuss more.
要多商量
Dad,
爸
you're right.
你说得对
That's what we were thinking.
我们是这么想的
Once we get the house,
这个房子到手之后啊
Meng'an and I won't rush into decorating.
我跟梦安也不着急去装
We'll wait
等想好了
until we're sure about everything
都想明白了
and make decisions,
都定下来了
then we'll start the work.
我们再动工
I'll go wash it now.
我去把它洗一洗啊
You sit and have some tea.
您坐会儿 喝喝茶
Does it look good?
好看吗
It looks beautiful.
好看是好看
But isn't it too warm?
热不热呀
For the sake of beauty,
为了美
I'll endure it.
忍了
It's fashion, you know?
这是时髦 你懂不懂
Mom,
老妈
are you okay?
你没事吧
You're back.
回来啦
Dad told me
我听老爸说
that you weren't feeling fine
你身体不舒服
and even went to the hospital.
都去医院了
Who went to the hospital?
谁去医院了
What's wrong?
哪儿不舒服啊
Dad said
我爸说
mom might be in menopause.
我妈好像更年期了
Are you really going through menopause?
你真的更年期啦
No.
没有
I just went to the hospital
就 就是去医院
to get some vitamins.
开了点维生素
Don't listen to your dad's nonsense.
别听你爸在那儿胡咧咧
It was a false alarm.
虚惊一场
I mean,
我要说
if you really were in menopause,
你要是真更年期了
I would try not to upset you.
我就少气气你
You better not upset me anyway.
那你还是少气气我吧
Menopause or not, I'm having a mood swing.
更年期很怕生气的
So, are you or aren't you?
你到底更没更
None of your business.
要你管
You're my sister or what?
你是我姐啊
Where's dad?
我爸呢
He's in the kitchen with Li Lin.
和李临在厨房呢
I'll go say hi.
我去打个招呼
Dad.
爸
Is she really in menopause?
真的更年期啦
Impossible. She's not that age yet.
不可能 没到岁数呢
Yunjie,
云阶
try not to bother your mom too much.
你最近少惹你妈啊
Today, she came in with such
今天一进来 那
a bad temper,
暴脾气啊
like she's in menopause.
像更年期啊
Dad.
爸
You're back.
回来啦
Why didn't I see Haowen?
怎么没看见浩文啊
He said he has a meeting.
他说他开会
He'll be back later.
晚点回来
Do you need help?
要帮忙不
No.
不用
Why did you tell the kid
你怎么跟孩子说我
that I'm going through menopause?
更年期了呢
Li Lin,
李临
let it soak for a bit longer
那个 你多泡一会儿
and spit out the sand,
让它吐吐沙子
then I'll cook it.
然后我来做
Alright.
行
Menopause
更年期
isn't shameful, is it?
也不丢人吧
What's wrong?
怎么了
Before you come over,
你一会儿来之前啊
go home first,
先回趟家
and bring all the new things I bought
把我那些个新买的
that are yet to be opened.
没拆封的东西
Bring as much
都带上 拿过来
as you can.
能拿多少拿多少
What for?
要干吗
I'll explain later.
回头再跟你解释
Okay, got it.
好 知道了
Take it.
拿着
What for?
干吗呀
Your mom asked me to give this to you.
你妈让我给你的
I'm too old to spend your money.
我都多大了还花你们钱
No matter how old you are,
你多大不也是
you are a child of us.
爹妈的孩子吗
Your mom said,
你妈说呀
if you have money in your pocket,
兜里有钱
you won't panic.
心不慌
Take it.
拿着
The password is your mom's birthday.
密码是你妈的生日
You know it.
你知道
Dad.
爸
Dad, everything is washed.
爸 都洗好了
Just waiting for you to start cooking.
就等着您开锅了
Okay, okay, I'll cook.
好好好 我去做
Upset?
生气了
What I meant was
我说的是
it's possible.
有可能
This...
这
This is...
这是
From dad.
爸给的
You should keep it.
你收着吧
You're getting a bit gloomy, huh?
沉重了啊
It's not that serious, right?
不至于吧
It's not that big of a deal.
这多大点事啊
Just feel a bit ashamed.
就觉得挺没脸的
Who is feeling ashamed?
你说谁没脸呢
You feel ashamed?
你这就没脸了
Then I'd be
那我脸
a lot more shamed long ago.
早不知道上哪儿去了
What do you mean?
什么意思啊
Back when Haowen and I
那会儿我和老贾
were starting our business,
创业的时候
mom gave me money too.
妈也给我钱来着
You didn't know that, right?
不知道吧
Back then,
那会儿呀
mom was afraid you'd think she was biased.
妈就是怕你觉得她偏心
I just didn't tell you.
就没告诉你
When did this happen?
什么时候的事啊
When Haowen and I
我和老贾在
were at Sijiqing.
四季青的时候呀
Someone wanted to sell their stall,
有人要兑摊位
and we wanted to buy it but didn't have enough money.
我们想买 钱不够
Mom gave it to us.
妈就给我了
Back then, when I took money from mom and dad,
那会儿我拿爸妈的钱
it wasn't like how you are now.
可不像你现在这样
You guys were so young back then.
你们那会儿多年轻啊
Li Lin and I at this age,
我跟你姐夫这岁数
we still don't know
还不知道
when we can pay it back.
什么时候能还上
Why do you need to pay it back?
还什么还啊
Why are you thinking like Haowen?
你怎么跟老贾一样
I told Haowen back then,
我当时就跟老贾说了
when we didn't have money,
没钱的时候
we took from mom and dad
我们拿爸妈的钱
like it was our own.
就要像拿自己的钱一样
When we have money,
等我们有钱了
spending on mom and dad
给爸妈花钱
should be more generous
要比给我们自己
than spending on ourselves.
花钱还要大方
That's why you decorated mom and dad's house like this?
所以把爸妈家装成这样
Exactly.
对啊
We're family, after all.
一家人嘛
But your mindset now,
你现在这种心态
is like you don't consider us as family.
就是没把我们当一家人
Sister, you need to think long-term.
姐 你要往长远了看
Mom and dad are doing great.
你看爸妈这身子骨
At least
怎么说
they have another twenty to thirty years to go, right?
起码还有个二三十年吧
You can't just think about paying back the money,
你不能光想着还钱
you also have to fulfill your filial duties.
还得尽孝呢
Am I right?
我说得对吧
I thought you were hugging me.
我还以为你搂我呢
You have no manners at all.
一点规矩都不懂
Coming, coming.
来了 来了
Sister, take this.
姐 你拿着
Is there more food?
还有菜吗
Yes, yes.
还有 还有
Li Lin made a lot.
姐夫做了好多呢
The oysters are really fresh today.
今儿这生蚝可新鲜
Mom.
妈
If you want to sell the car,
你要卖车的话
I can recommend
我给你推荐个
a used car website for you.
二手车网站吧
You can sell it for more than
卖得比二手车
what you'd get at a used car market.
市场上高呢
We're not selling the car anymore.
咱家车不卖了
We'll keep driving this car
以后还开这辆车
to take you to school from now on.
送你上学
Really?
真的
Dad!
爸
Did you find a job?
你是找着工作了吗
Why didn't you tell me earlier?
你怎么不早说呀
I was worried about you!
我还担心你呢
Thinking the car would be sold,
说车卖了
and then how would I explain
到时候怎么跟
it to He Lu and the others?
何璐他们解释
Now it's fine,
这下好了
I can shop for other things.
我刷别的了
Yunjie,
云阶
you and your mom come out first.
你跟你妈妈先下
I'll go park the car.
我去停车
Wait a minute,
等一下
there's something from my aunt in the trunk.
后备箱有小姨送的东西
A gift from her?
送的东西
All these are gifts from aunt.
这都是小姨送的
So many.
这么多
Where did that pair of sneakers go?
有双球鞋哪里去了
Later, with all these things,
一会儿这些东西
I'll take as much as I can carry.
我能拿多少是多少啊
I can't carry everything,
我可拿不完
so I'll leave the rest to you two.
交给你俩了
Okay.
好
Honey.
老婆
What's up?
怎么了
You know,
你说
today we...
今天咱
We're giving gifts to my sister
咱给姐送礼
at such a sensitive time.
在这个敏感时期
Isn't that a bit inappropriate?
是不不太合适啊
Honey,
老婆
we didn't know
咱不是不知道
about her situation, right?
姐这特殊情况吗
Now that we know, we should give even more.
以后咱知道就得多送
I'm telling you,
我告诉你
Yunjie's food, drinks, necessities, clothes,
云阶的吃 喝 用 穿
are all covered.
全包了
You don't understand my sister.
你不了解我姐
My sister has a strong sense of pride.
我姐她自尊心强
Just today,
就今天
when we had mom and dad give her the money,
咱让爸妈给那钱
it almost got rejected.
都差点没送出去
My sister has been working part-time
我姐从大学起
to support herself since college.
就开始勤工俭学了
Asking family for money
你让她问家里人
would
伸手要钱
really hurt her.
那是戳她心窝子的
Then we have to help her get used to it,
那咱就得让姐习惯呀
because family shouldn't stand on ceremony.
一家人不说两家话
Why should she feel embarrassed
怎么就不好意思
to ask her own family for help?
给自己家人张嘴了
From now on, her matters
以后姐家的事
are our matters.
就是咱的事
I'm telling you,
我告诉你啊
tomorrow I'll give my brother-in-law
明儿我还要给姐夫
more gifts.
再去送
Enough, enough, enough.
算算算
Even my sister didn't accept it.
我姐都不收
With his pride, would he accept it?
姐夫那脸皮 他能要啊
He's thin-skinned.
他脸皮薄啊
I'm thick-skinned.
我脸皮厚
I don't care.
我不管
In this world,
天底下
there's no gift that Jia Haowen
就没有我贾浩文
can't give away.
送不出去的礼
Let me tell you,
我跟你讲啊
gift-giving is an art.
送礼是艺术
You're quite an artist, huh?
你挺懂艺术啊
Where's mine?
我的呢
What?
什么呀
It's on the way.
在路上
I've got a surprise for you.
给你个惊喜
Come back!
回来
What is it? Tell me quickly,
是什么赶紧说
or I won't be able to sleep tonight.
不然我晚上睡不着觉
Miss Xu Mengxin,
许梦心小姐
please open your phone
请打开您的手机
and check your shopping cart.
看一下您的购物车
Surprised?
惊不惊喜
Isn't it unexpected?
意不意外啊
As expected.
意料之中
Watching Chang'e?
看嫦娥呢
Watching the stars.
看星星呢
Let me tell you,
我跟你说啊
today, when you asked me to give that...
今天你不是让我把那个
that card
那个卡
to the eldest, right?
给老大吗
You know what I was thinking before that?
给她以前我想啥吗
What were you thinking?
想啥
I was thinking,
我就想啊
with her personality,
就以老大那个性格
she wouldn't want it.
她不会要
She'd definitely
她肯定要跟我
argue with me.
撕撕巴巴的
You know?
你知道吧
I even thought,
我还想呢
how could I convince her?
我怎么说服她
But I didn't expect that
但是我没想到
when I took out the card,
当时我把这个卡拿出来
I said,
我说
"Your mom asked me to give this to you."
是你妈让我给你的
What did she say?
她怎么说啊
She didn't say anything.
老大啥也没说
I just grabbed her hand back,
我就把这个
holding it in mine, saying
她的手拽回来
"Take it.
拿着
The password is your mom's birthday."
密码是你妈的生日
I then
我就把手
closed her hand.
给她合上了
When I looked up,
我一抬头
she was crying.
孩子哭了
This means something serious is going on.
这就是真有事
Otherwise,
要不然的话
she wouldn't have taken the money.
她不会要这个钱
Then I started thinking about Li Lin.
我就再联想到李临
He's not like going to work.
他不好好地上班
He gets up in the morning...
他早晨起来
It's not Sunday.
又不是礼拜天
It's not Saturday either.
又不是礼拜六
How could he go buy groceries?
他能上超市去买菜去
And also buy those
而且还去买那个
discounted eggs.
打折的鸡蛋
Yes, yes.
对对对
I ran into him.
我碰上了
Didn't I tell you?
跟你说过吧
Yes, you told me.
对 你跟我说过
Why isn't he at work?
为什么不上班
Maybe something happened
那就是可能是
at his company, right?
公司出问题了呗
Perhaps,
他没准
just like in that comedy sketch,
真是跟那小品说的
he got "gloriously laid off."
光荣地下岗了
Could that be possible?
会不会有这种可能啊
What should we do?
这可怎么办哪
Yeah.
对呀
Just think about how much this weighs on him
你说他这心得多重啊
right now.
现在
How big a deal it must be
得多大的事
to get him like this.
把孩子整成这样了
She is just same as him.
老大和他都一样
They won't talk about anything.
什么事都不肯说
You know,
你说
this eldest one,
这个老大
she is so strong-willed.
又那么要强
And Li Lin, being a researcher,
你说李临一个搞科研的
is so single-minded, you know?
一根筋 你知道吗
I'm just thinking,
我就想啊
how to properly talk to him.
怎么跟他说合适
I just thought of something.
我刚才呀 想了一句话
What is it?
什么话
Actually, it wasn't my idea.
其实这话也不是我想的
I saw it on my phone.
我也是看那手机上
It says,
说
"Don't be a..."
不要当一个
How does it go again?
那句话怎么说着
Let me think...
我想想啊
Don't...
不要
Don't be a...
不要当一个
highly educated fool.
高学历的傻瓜
No, isn't that an insult?
不是 你这不骂人吗
No, see, you're just at primary level.
不 你看你就小学水平
How is that an insult?
这怎么是骂人呢
What I mean is,
我是说的意思说
a person shouldn't study too much,
人不能把书读多了
or they'll become foolish.
就读傻了
That's what I mean.
是这个意思
I think this saying
我觉得这句话
suits him perfectly now.
现在特别适合他
He's just read too many books.
他就是书读得太多了
I'm afraid he won't figure it out,
我是怕他想不开
you know?
你知道吗
If he's depressed all day,
一天郁闷郁闷
he might get sick.
他再得病了
What if there's something wrong here,
就这儿再有点毛病
and something wrong there?
这儿再有点毛病
What would we do about our eldest then?
那咱家老大怎么办呢
Then you should go talk to him quickly!
那你赶紧找他谈谈去啊
Do you think if I say this...
你觉得我这么说
Is it okay?
行不行
Yeah.
行
Okay, okay.
行行
He won't understand like you do, right?
他不会像你这么理解吧
Thinking I'm insulting him.
说我骂他
Well, there aren't many like me, you know.
那那 像我的没几个呀
Okay.
行
Tomorrow when I go to work,
我明天上班的时候
this plan
这个方案
must be on
就要出现在
my desk.
我的办公桌上
Alright?
好吧
Come on, come on, come on!
加油 加油 加油
Let's all work hard together!
一起加油啊
As for your job,
你那工作啊
just quit it.
你就给辞了吧
We don't need your small income.
咱家不缺你这点钱
This is the divorce agreement
这是我让律师
drafted by my lawyer.
起草的离婚协议书
Take a look.
看看吧
Don't scare me!
你别吓唬我啊
I'm not scaring you.
我没吓唬你
I've made up my mind.
我下决心了
I'm definitely
这个婚
getting a divorce.
我一定离
No,
不是
is it necessary?
至于吗
Do we really need
咱们俩至于到
to go as far as getting a divorce?
离婚的这份上吗
Do you think our marriage
你觉得我们的婚姻
still have a reason to exist?
还有存在的必要吗
Of course it does.
当然了
Our child is only eight years old.
咱们俩孩子才八岁
Yes,
是
I work outside every day,
我每天我在外面工作
and I rarely come home.
我很少回家
But you wouldn't think
但是你不会认为
I have something going on outside, right?
我在外面有什么事吧
Do I have anything going on outside?
我在外边我有什么事啊
This...
这
Where did this come from?
哪儿来的
You don't need to know that.
这个你没必要知道
You men,
你们男人
are you all like this?
是不是都这样啊
Don't shed tears until you see the coffin.
不见棺材不掉泪
No, Wanzhen, I...
不 婉真我
I, I, I swear to you,
我 我 我向你发誓啊
I absolutely did nothing wrong to you,
我绝对没有干对不起你
or to
或者是对不起
this family of ours.
咱这家庭的事
You know, in the business world,
你说 这在生意场上
sometimes,
那就是有的时候
there are men and women,
男男女女的
it's just playing along, right?
这不就是逢场作戏吗
Indeed, sometimes,
的确有的时候
when I'm tired,
我累的时候
I also need
也是需要
someone to take care of me, right?
别人来照顾我的
Right?
对吧
But between me and her,
但是我跟她之间
there is absolutely nothing
绝对没有什么
crossing the line.
实质上的事
This trust
这 这个信任
should always exist between us, right?
咱们之间总是会有的吧
Are you saying this is all a misunderstanding?
你是说这都是误会
It's a coincidence
这是巧合
that it happened to be photographed, right?
恰好被拍到了是吧
No, look
不 你看呀
at the environment...
这环境
This is a hotel I often stay in.
这是我 长包那个酒店
Men and women here
每天进进出出
are so many.
男男女女多少人呀
When working overtime,
加起班来
it's day and night
那就是不分日
without fail, right?
不分夜的 对吧
If there's a woman
你说 有这么个女的
in my room
在我房间里
taking these kinds of photos,
拍了这样的照片
you can't throw all this dirt
你不能把这脏水
just on me, can you?
都泼我一人头上吧
I'll sack her tomorrow.
我明天我就把她辞了
Wanzhen.
婉真
I really didn't know.
我真的不知道
I didn't know
我不知道
you've endured so much.
你承受了这么多
Yu Hai,
于海
you think by
你以为你把
sacking Miss Huang,
黄小姐辞退了
we can pretend
我们就可以当
nothing happened
什么都没有发生
and live like before?
还像以前一样生活吗
No, Wanzhen,
不是 婉真
in my heart,
你在我心里
you have always been my wife.
一直都是我的老婆
I admit, I admit I was wrong.
我承认 我承认我错了
Alright.
好吧
I was wrong, I was wrong.
我错了 我错了
I, I, I...
我 我 我
I became arrogant,
我自己膨胀
I became vain.
我爱慕虚荣
Sometimes, I even...
我有的时候 我甚至
I enjoy having someone by my side.
我享受身边有那么个人
But I'll change.
但是我改
I swear on my health,
我以我的健康发誓
I, Yu Hai, have my limits.
我于海是有底线的
I absolutely...
我绝
I know what you're going to say.
我知道你要说什么
You have your limits.
你是有底线的
You didn't physically cheat,
你身体没有出轨
you just had a little
你只是精神上
lapse emotionally.
开了一个小差
That's what you mean, right?
你是这个意思吧
Yu Hai,
于海
I don't care who you are now.
你现在是什么样的人
I don't care at all.
我根本就不在乎
And don't try to
你也不要试图来
save this marriage.
挽回这段婚姻
No, why?
不 为什么呀
Why?
为什么
Why do we have to
为什么咱就非得
get a divorce?
离这个婚呢
Wanzhen, you weren't like this before.
婉真 以前你不这样
You always considered the bigger picture.
你都是顾全大局的
You were so sensible.
你很懂事
You, divorce...
你 离婚
You still have to think about the child
你 你总得为孩子
and the elders, right?
为老人考虑一下吧
I was just too sensible before,
我就是之前太懂事了
too concerned about the bigger picture.
太顾全大局了
I've always compromised,
我一直委曲求全
why can't I
我为什么不能
have my own life?
拥有自己的生活
Do I have to live
我就必须以
as Mrs. Yu?
于太太的身份
I don't want
来生活吗
this identity anymore.
我不想要这个身份了
I want to be Chen Wanzhen again.
我想做回陈婉真
No, no, no, Wanzhen,
别别别 婉真
Wanzhen, Wanzhen, Wanzhen!
婉真 婉真 婉真
Don't scare me like this.
你别吓唬我
We've been together
咱们俩在一起
for ten years.
生活十年了
The child is only eight now,
孩子现在只有八岁
right?
对吧
I'm busy outside every day,
我每天在外边忙
and the house is entirely up to you.
家完全交给了你
You are my pillar of support.
你就是我的顶梁柱
Everything I have,
我的所有
my home,
我的家
my career.
我的事业
Everything I have
我的一切
is tied together with yours.
咱们都是绑定在一起的
Yes, I'm busy now,
是 我现在忙
and I rarely come home.
我很少回家
But don't think
你不要认为
that this makes our
这样咱俩之间的
relationship fade.
情感就淡了
Don't let this be the reason
你别因为这个
we split up, okay?
咱俩就离 好吧
Is it...
是不是 是不是
because of the issue with mom?
因为妈妈这段
But, between us,
不是 咱俩之间
there's always mutual responsibility, right?
总有互相的这个责任吧
Feelings are feelings,
感情是感情
marriage is marriage.
婚姻是婚姻
What I'm talking about
我跟你说的是
is the marriage itself.
婚姻的事情
I don't want to be trapped
我不想困在
in this marriage with you anymore.
和你的这段婚姻里了
I want to leave.
我想离开
No, why should you?
不 那凭什么呀
Why you say leave
凭什么你要离开
and we have to leave?
你就离开呀
Moreover,
再说了
after you leave me,
你 你 你离开我之后
how will you live?
你怎么生活啊
Yu Hai, are you afraid that
于海 你是不是怕我
I'll take your money?
分走你的钱啊
No.
不
I'm afraid of you?
我怕你
Afraid of you, what for?
我怕你什么呀
I can earn money myself.
我自己能挣钱
Even if I
我即使
give everything to you
我把所有的东西
and leave with nothing,
都给你了
I can still
我净身出户
rise again,
我依然能够东山再起
okay?
好不好
Aren't you afraid
那你就不怕
of the board and the shareholders?
董事会和股东吗
No,
不是
what do you really mean?
你到底什么意思啊
I've already discussed with the lawyer
我和律师已经商量了
about the divorce agreement.
离婚协议
If you sign,
如果你签
I'll only take the house and savings.
我只拿走房产跟积蓄
I waive my share in the company
我放弃公司的股份
and the added value portion.
和增值的部分
The company remains yours.
公司还是你的
Your shareholders.
你的股东
Your investors.
你的投资人
You can all rest reassured.
都可以放心
If you don't sign,
如果不签
we'll see you in court.
咱们就法院见
You better think over it.
你自己掂量吧
That is
你们是
Hongsheng Medical Equipment, right?
鸿升医疗器械 是吧
Yes.
是
Did you see the job posting?
您是看到招聘信息了吗
I saw it online.
我在网上看见的
Right, right, I...
对 对啊 我
I'm a man.
我男同志
If you still need someone,
如果你们还需要的话呢
give me a call, okay?
给我打个电话好吗
Who is it?
谁啊
Hello, sir.
先生 您好
Your delivery has arrived.
您外卖到了
I didn't order any delivery.
我没点外卖
Isn't this
您这不是
Room 502, Unit 2?
二单元五零二吗
You got it wrong.
搞错了
This is Unit 1.
这里是一单元
Unit 2 is next door.
二单元在隔壁
Sorry, sorry.
不好意思 不好意思
I'm new here.
刚来这边 不熟悉
You...
你
are working with a child?
带着孩子干活啊
Her mother is in the neighboring complex.
她妈妈在隔壁小区
Working as a housekeeper.
做家政呢
Sorry about that.
不好意思啊
Sorry to disturb you.
打扰了 打扰了
Director Xu.
许总监
What are you eating?
吃什么呢
There's roast duck here.
这儿有烧鸭
Do you want some?
你要不要来一点
It's really delicious.
可香了
Have a piece.
来一块 来一块
Director Xu.
许总监
No, no.
不了 不了
You guys eat.
你们吃吧 你们吃吧
Hello, Director Xu.
许总监好
Qianqian.
倩倩
Your pork knuckle rice.
你的猪脚饭
Thank you.
谢谢
Here you go.
给
Want some, Director Xu?
吃吗 许总监
Keep eating.
吃吃吃
Come over, come over.
快过来 快过来
Let me tell you...
我跟你说啊
I spent two months gathering the courage.
我鼓了两个月勇气
Today, I finally decided
今天终于决定
to eat a leek pie.
吃一顿韭菜盒子
Come on, hurry up.
来 快点
What's wrong?
怎么了
What are you doing?
你干吗呀
You got it all over my
都弄到我的
leek pie!
韭菜盒子里了
Seriously!
你真是的
Are you pregnant?
你怀孕啦
Really?
真的假的
When did this happen?
什么时候的事啊
How long has it been?
多长时间了
Is it a boy or a girl?
男孩女孩啊
It's still just a tiny speck now.
现在还是个豆丁呢
Okay?
好吗
Hurry up
你赶紧
and clean this up for me.
把这都给我收起来
Clean it up.
收起来
Okay, okay, okay.
好好好
Li Lin, you did well.
李临可以啊
What does this have to do with Li Lin?
这跟李临有什么关系啊
How is it unrelated?
怎么没关系啊
Without Li Lin, could you have gotten pregnant?
没李临 你能怀上啊
That's because I'm healthy, okay?
那是我身体好 好吗
That's great!
太好了
Hurry up and give birth!
赶紧生吧
My future retirement
我未来的养老
now has more security.
又多了一份保障啊
On behalf of all future elders,
我要替未来所有老人
thank you
感谢你
for your great contribution
为社会做出了
to society.
巨大的贡献
You're thanking me too soon.
你谢谢早了
I don't plan to give birth.
我没想生
Why not?
为什么呀
Is it your business?
管着吗
Don't be stubborn.
你别赌气嘛
It's a good thing!
这是好事啊
Is it because of the morning sickness?
因为孕吐难受是吧
From now on, no one in the company
以后公司所有人
is allowed to eat leek pies.
不许吃韭菜盒子
I'm telling you,
我跟你说
your morning sickness,
你这个孕吐啊
a while ago
前一段时间
you didn't have this reaction.
还没有这个反应呢
It's definitely because you got the good news,
肯定是因为中标了
you relaxed,
精神放松了
and that's why you have this reaction.
才有了这个反应
It's not a big deal.
不要紧的啊
Your work will pick up soon.
你这工作马上就会接上
The morning sickness will be resolved easily.
孕吐 就会迎刃而解
Isn't that too much?
过分了吧
I came to you just to talk about
我来找你就是想说
the leave of absence.
请假的事呢
You really don't want it?
真不要了呀
If it were you,
要是你的话
would you want it?
你要吗
Yes, I would.
要啊
I haven't had one yet.
我还没生过呢
I mean a second child.
我说二胎
Second child.
二胎
You'd better help me calculate
你还是先帮我算算
how long I can take leave.
我能请多长时间假吧
If you really don't want the child,
你要真不要这孩子
it's definitely not a matter of two or three days.
那肯定不是两三天的事
It would take at least a month or so.
怎么也得个把月吧
I can calculate
我可以给你算算
how much leave you have,
你有多少假
but I can't approve it.
但我批不了呀
This matter
这事
still needs to go to Zhang.
还是得找老张
Success in certain fields,
自己在某些领域的成功
one would think
他会认为
is due to his diligence,
是他的勤奋
hard work, and struggle.
努力和拼搏
But does this explanation hold water?
但这个解释说得过去吗
We never said
我们从来没有说
effort is not important.
努力不重要啊
Because it's so important,
因为它太重要了
it's unnecessary to tell you.
重要到不需要告诉你
Who doesn't work hard in China?
在中国谁不努力
Who doesn't work hard in Shenzhen?
在深圳谁不努力
Who?
谁啊
Sir,
先生
would you like a wooden comb?
要木梳吗
Do you have one made of peach wood?
有桃木的吗
We're on the same side.
自己人
Hi Dad.
爸
Were you
你这
going fishing?
钓鱼去啦
Why is it so dark in here?
这屋怎么这么黑呀
Take off your glasses.
您把眼镜摘了
They all left.
都走了
Went to work.
该上班上班
Went to school.
该上学上学
Come with me.
跟我走
What for?
干吗呀
Roast chicken.
烧鸡
Take the fishing rod.
拿上钓鱼竿
Let's go.
走
Where are we going?
干吗去啊
Fishing!
钓鱼去啊
But you already have fish.
你这不有鱼了吗
Bought from the market.
菜市场买的
Come on, let's go, let's go.
走走走 我们走
Wait for me.
你等我
Very good.
很好
I'm going to change my clothes.
我换个衣服啊
Okay.
好的
Dad.
爸
I'm unemployed.
我失业了
Shake hands.
握握手
Shake hands?
握手
Come on.
来
Congratulations on being unemployed.
恭喜你失业
Congratulations, congratulations, congratulations.
恭喜 恭喜 恭喜
Congratulations?
恭喜我
Congratulations, congratulations.
恭喜 恭喜
Who hasn't been unemployed?
谁没失过业呀
I've been unemployed too.
我也失过业呀
Back then, your mom and I
当年我跟你妈俩
were both unemployed together
一起都失业了
when we were in the Northeast.
在东北的时候
It's no big deal.
这都不是事
What's the big deal?
这是啥事
A few days ago, I came to fish.
前两天我来钓鱼
That day, the fog was quite thick.
那天雾比较大
Then from the bridge over there,
然后从桥那边
a small boat came over.
就过来了一条小船
When it got there,
等到那儿的时候
I saw an old man
我一看有一个
with a white beard,
白胡子老人
wearing a bamboo hat
戴着一个斗笠
and a raincoat, fishing there.
穿着蓑衣在那儿钓鱼
I looked closely.
我这一看
The old man had a fishing rod and a hook,
这老头有鱼竿 有钩
but the hook was straight.
但他那钩是直的
Three feet above the water.
离水三尺
I said, fishing like this,
我说你这样钓
can you catch any fish?
你能钓着鱼吗
The old man said,
老人家说
you're fishing for fish.
你是在钓鱼
I'm fishing for an opportunity.
我是在钓一个机会
I said, I often fish here.
我说我在这儿经常钓鱼
Why have I never seen you?
怎么从来没见过你啊
I asked, what's your surname?
我说你姓啥呀
Surnamed Jiang.
姓姜
It was at this moment...
就这时候
Bang! I fell to the ground.
咣当我掉地下了
I woke up, you know?
醒了我就 你知道吧
No, no, no,
不是 不是 不是
after that,
他后边
did he catch any opportunity?
钓没钓着机会呀他
This I know.
这个我知道
Jiang Taigong fishing: the willing bite the hook.
姜太公钓鱼 愿者上钩
What does this mean exactly?
这啥意思啊 到底是
Dad.
爸
Before, I
我之前
didn't tell you
之所以没有告诉你
that I was unemployed
我失业了
because I didn't want
我就是不想
to make you worry about this.
让你们为我这个事操心
But I know, Dad,
但我知道 爸
what you both are thinking.
你们是怎么想的
These past few days,
这两天
you've been beating around the bush.
你这旁敲侧击的
I roughly understand now.
我大概就明白了
Opportunity
机会
isn't just waiting there for me.
不是在那儿等着我
is something I have to create myself.
得我自己去创造
I understand.
我懂
Yes.
对
The ancients could wait for opportunities,
古人可以等这个机会
but you young people today,
你们现在年轻人
you can't wait for opportunities.
不能等机会
You have to actively and diligently
得积极地 努力地
seek out opportunities.
去寻找机会
Is that what you mean?
你是这意思吧
Dad.
爸
Today, now that I've said it, I
今天我说出来了 我
feel pretty good.
我挺舒服的
It's not just that you've been feeling unwell.
不光你这几天不舒服
I too wasn't feeling good playing chess with you.
我跟你下棋我都不舒服
You kept spacing out every day.
你一天老跑神
I was just afraid you were getting sick, you know?
我就是怕你得什么病啊
Son, you know?
孩子 你知道吗
Let me tell you.
我跟你说
If a door closes for you,
给你关上了一扇门
a window will open.
就打开了一扇窗
When I was laid off back then,
当时我下岗的时候
I kept telling myself,
我就自己告诫我自己
I'm gold,
我是金子
I will shine.
我要发光
With that mindset,
这样的话
your confidence
你的自信心
will grow stronger and stronger.
就会越来越强大
Right?
是不是
Back then, my grandfather
我爷爷那时候
used to always tell me one thing:
就经常跟我说一句话
When you succeed,
人 你成功了
don't get too cocky.
别太嘚瑟
When you don't succeed,
不成功了
don't abandon yourself either.
也不要把自己丢弃
Right?
对不对
If one path doesn't work out,
说你这条路走不通了
try another path.
你换条路
You'll still see poetry and distant places.
它一样能看见
Poetry and distant places.
诗和远方
I'm making a fool of myself.
班门弄斧
But these words,
但是这几句话
I've thought about them for several days.
我想了好几天
You know?
你知道吗
For several days?
想了好几天
Right. It's got some depth, right?
对 还有点水平吧
Very deep.
太有水平了
Now I've had a sudden realization.
我现在是茅塞顿开
A sudden realization.
茅塞顿开
My son-in-law praises me...
大姑爷能表扬我
You've got drinks?
还喝点吗
I'm happy.
我高兴
Let's celebrate.
庆祝一下
Okay, let's celebrate this.
好 庆祝一下这
Looks like I brought the right wine today.
看来今天这酒我拿对了
I originally wanted to drink a bit of sorrow wine with you,
我本来想跟你喝点闷酒
but it turned into a celebratory drink.
这变成释放酒了
Come on.
来来来
For poetry
为诗
and distant places.
和远方
Dad.
爸
With you around,
有您在
it's really good.
真好
In our position,
我们这个岗位
it seems like we need to travel at any time.
好像需要随时出差
That's great!
那太好了
While working,
工作的时候
you can also go out and explore.
还能出去转转
Anyway, I'm not married.
反正我也没结婚
I'm alone.
一个人
Who isn't?
谁还不是呢
I'm really sorry about this time.
这次实在是抱歉啊
It's also quite a pity.
也比较可惜
If next time we have
如果我们下次有
a better position and opportunity,
更好的岗位和机会
we'll definitely contact you first.
肯定第一时间联系你
Where are you going?
你干吗去啊
Someone introduced me to a job.
别人给我介绍一个活
At the courier transfer station near our home.
在家附近的快递中转站
Courier?
快递
Are you going to deliver packages?
你要去送快递吗
I'm not delivering packages.
我不送快递
Courier transfer station.
快递中转站
Aren't they all receiving goods at night?
不都是晚上接货吗
I'm matching the orders for them.
我给他们对单子
Just enter the tracking number
把这个单号
directly into the computer, that's all.
直接输到电脑里就行了
Very easy.
很轻松
Clerical work.
文职工作
It's so late.
这么晚了
Do you really have to go?
你一定要去吗
I want to go.
我想去
Meng'an,
梦安
your dad was right.
你爸说得挺对的
At my age,
我到这个岁数了
finding a job
要找个工作
is really not easy.
还真挺不容易的
People
人嘛
have to swallow their pride.
不能老端着
When it's time to be humble,
该放下的时候
you have to be humble, right?
就得放下 是吧
I gotta go.
来不及了 到点了啊
Don't worry. It's very easy.
你放心 很轻松的
Maybe, if it's quick,
没准 快的话
I'll be back in the middle of the night.
我后半夜就回来了
You rest early.
你早点休息
I'm off.
走了